<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peoples zeal provok't to an holy emulation by the pious and instructive example of their dead minister, or, A seasonable memento to the parishioners of Lavenham in Suffolk being a sermon preached to that people, soon after the solemn enterrment of their Reverand and pious minister, Mr. William Gurnall, who aged 63, died October 12, 1679 : and now at their request made publick / by William Burkitt ...</title>
            <author>Burkitt, William, 1650-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36338</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15666620</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15666620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104311</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1181:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peoples zeal provok't to an holy emulation by the pious and instructive example of their dead minister, or, A seasonable memento to the parishioners of Lavenham in Suffolk being a sermon preached to that people, soon after the solemn enterrment of their Reverand and pious minister, Mr. William Gurnall, who aged 63, died October 12, 1679 : and now at their request made publick / by William Burkitt ...</title>
                  <author>Burkitt, William, 1650-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.W. for Ralph Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Running title: The dead speaking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gurnall, William, 1617-1679.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Peoples Zeal Provok't TO AN Holy Emulation, By the Pious and Inſtructive Example of their dead MINISTER: OR A Seaſonable Memento to the Pariſhioners of <hi>Lavenham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi> BEING A SERMON Preached to that People, ſoon after the Solemn Enterrment of their Reverend and Pious Miniſter, Mr. <hi>William Gurnall;</hi> Who Aged 63, Died <hi>October</hi> 12. 1679.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi>
               </bibl> Abel being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <bibl>Ignat. <hi>Epiſt. ad Phil.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>And now at their requeſt made publick, by <hi>William Burkitt,</hi> M. A. of <hi>Pembrook</hi> Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Mildin</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M.W.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the Bible under the <hi>Piazza</hi> of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:2"/>
            <head>To my Honoured Friend M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Sarah Gurnall,</hi> the ſorrowful Relict of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Gurnal,</hi> late of <hi>Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> deceaſed; and to the reſt of the ſurviving Inhabitants of that Town.</head>
            <p>THAT I appeared no ſooner in the Croud of Mourners, to condole with you in your publick loſs; it was becauſe I would not rudely diſturb the motions of ſo juſt a ſorrow. It hath been long obſerved, that during the prevalency of exceſſive grief, the ſoul hath no leiſure to attend to thoſe advices; which (when the floods of ſorrow are a little dried up) are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeaſonable but advantagious. May what is here then, modeſtly preſented to your impartial view, be like the Rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> to divide the waters of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or like the Mantle of <hi>Elijah</hi> to reſtrain thoſe ſloods of your immoderate grief, which will be too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to overflow their banks, if Reaſon and Religion do not prevent by a ſeaſonable interpoſure. But I am very willing to perſwade my ſelf that Almighty God hath wrought your hearts to ſuch a chearful temper, as may give an obedient welcom to this ſo
<pb facs="tcp:104311:3"/>ſmarting an affliction; that even whilſt you weep, you may yet ſmile upon the Rod of your Heavenly Father, whoſe ſtripes you do ſo tenderly ſuffer; and enabled you alſo to bring your minds to a willing and contented acquieſcency in the wiſdom of divine appointments: how croſs and contradictory ſoever they may ſeem to rebellious nature. 'Tis eaſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for thoſe whoſe bones are full of marrow, to be joyful, but for the bones which God hath broken to rejoyce, is queſtionleſs the praiſe of Divine Mercy; to be not only patient, but praiſeful under ſo ſevere and killing a diſpenſation, is certainly the higheſt pitch of Chriſtian Fortitude; to ſmile upon afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and under its ſevereſt preſſures, to ſing when others ſhriek, will eminently beſpeak you a ſingular pattern of holy chearfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Yet withall underſtand and know, that the ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of Chriſtianity doth allow you to expreſs your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful reſentments of the abſence and loſs of your uſeful Friend: and it is a truth by the common conſent of all mankind acknowledged, that there is no burthen ſo abſolutely intolerable to humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as the death and ſeparation of thoſe whom Gods Honourable Ordinance hath conjoyned and made one, the bonds of Matrimonial Love, being ſtronger than thoſe of Nature. How often have we ſeen men of noble and gallant ſpirits, able to ſcorn inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and bravely to conquer, yea to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the baſe attempts of malice; by not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing ſo much as to take any notice of them: yet how have their generous minds been diſconſolately dejected, when the doleful tidings of their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons death have firſt ſurprized them? The victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:104311:3"/>
               <hi>David,</hi> who was no whit aſtoniſhed at the great <hi>Goliahs</hi> valour, nor his Attendants rage, but with an undaunted reſolution (though but a Stripling) encounters with him, and utterly overthrows him; yet when the ſad and ſudden news came of the death of his beloved <hi>Jonathan,</hi> ſorrow like a thick Cloud ſate upon his Countenance,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.26.</note> and the bitter anguiſh of his painful ſoul conſtrained him to cry out, <hi>I am di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, the holy Jeſus, that grand exemplar of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who always ſubmitted to his Fathers will in all things, and therefore could never be ſubject to the corroding thoughts of diſcontent, yet he by his own practice, ſhewed the propenſity of our natures to grief and ſorrow, for the loſs of thoſe whom we highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and dearly love; he himſelf paſſionately weeping when his beloved <hi>Lazarus</hi> lay aſleep in the ſilent dormitory of the Grave,
<note place="margin">St. Joh. 11.35.</note> and the chorus of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſtood lamenting him.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Religion doth not deſtroy humane paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and natural affections, which were originally planted in innocent nature, and were afterwards found in Chriſts ſpotleſs nature; yea ſo far are they from being ſinful, that they are highly uſeful when kept (as they ought to be) under the Lock and Key of Reaſon: then it is that our paſſions become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, when they become exceſſive, and grow impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of reſtraint by the ſuperiour powers and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mans ſoul, when the dictates of reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail nothing, but the Prince Lackeys after the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and paſſion uſurps the Throne, whoſe place is no higher than the Foot-ſtool.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:4"/>
            <p>Thus I obſerve good <hi>Jacob</hi> guilty of too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to his natural affection, when he ſorrowfully cries out like a man reſolved to exaſperate his own miſeries,
<note place="margin">Gen. 37.35.</note> 
               <hi>I will go down into the grave, unto my Son mourning:</hi> for the truth is, as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of any paſſion is ſinful and injurious, ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate ſorrow is particularly hurtful to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and diſhonourable to the dead; neither is it an argument of more Love, but an evidence of leſs Grace.</p>
            <p>You may pleaſe to remark the difference between the <hi>Egyptians</hi> mourning,
<note place="margin">Gen. 50.3. &amp; 10. compared.</note> and <hi>Joſephs</hi> for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob;</hi> they mourned ſeventy days for the old Patriarch, he but ſeven days for his own Father: What! Did Heatheniſm outdo Religion? or had ſtrangers more natural affection than his own Bowels? I hope not ſo. But Joſephs piety prevails above his paſſion, and the certain knowledge of his holy Fathers joyful reſurrection (which they were ignorant wholly of) adminiſtred more matter of comfort, than his death could occaſion ſorrow. <hi>Joſeph</hi> knew that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Tears were the prodigality of affection; he knew the unprofitableneſs as well as the impiety of a ſullen ſorrow; he knew that could he have melted himſelf into tears or by weeping have occaſioned a ſecond Deludge, yet all would have been in vain. <hi>Orpheus</hi> in the Ethnick Mythology could make Trees and Stones dance after the Muſick of his Harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lute, yet could not with all his Melodious Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony reduce his deceaſed Friends from the power of the Grave: for the houſe of death is like the Lyons Cave, from whence there are no returning Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:4"/>
            <p>Seeing then that the Supreme Majeſty (whoſe paths are in the labyrinths of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſearchable Wiſdom, and whoſe footſteps are like the track of a mighty ſhip in the over-ſwelling Ocean, paſt finding out) hath by the late iſſue of his Providence declared his will, it is moſt reaſonable that this declaration of Gods will ſhould ſatisfactorily determine yours: for remember that when God rings changes in a Town, he well knows how to make Muſick thereby to his own Glory: and in the intervals of paſſion, let me beg of you to conſider, that a juſt and pious imitation of his holy example, whom God hath removed from you, is the important duty which now lies incumbent upon you, with a perſevering diligence to perform.</p>
            <p>To Inform and Convince you how highly account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able you are to almighty God, both for the long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of his Miniſtry, and alſo for the happy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his example, is the honeſt deſign of the following Sermon: and alſo to let this cenſorious age, (in which ſome perſons are ſo overgrown with the Anti-Epiſcopal Jaundice, that their Eye can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a Conformiſt, but what is diſcoloured and of a different tincture) underſtand and know that you had a Conformiſt for your Miniſter, who rendred ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Religion amiable, by a Converſation in all things worthy of it; who did by a Regular Piety, a ſtrict Sobriety, a Catholick and diffuſive Charity, render Religion venerable to the world; one whoſe whole time, ſtrength and parts, were piouſly devoted to God and his ſacred Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> I obſerve, was in one particular priviledged by God above all other holy perſons: their ſouls (in common with his) at death have Angels for their
<pb facs="tcp:104311:5"/>Convoy towards the Manſions of Bliſs and Glory: but he had an Angel for his Sexton, who buried his Body in an unknown place, leſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould ſuperſtitiouſly Idolize and adore it: There would be no fear at all of any ſuch offenſive adoration on your part, were I able (as indeed I am not) to draw to the life the fair Effigies of your abſent Miniſter, who was, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> faithful in all Gods houſe whilſt he lived, and not unlike him at his death; his meek ſoul gliding from him in a fine imperceptible vehicle, and he dying as the modern Jews by tradition tell us <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>ad Nutum Dei, &amp; Oſculo Oris ejus,</hi> at Gods beck, and as it were with a kiſs of Gods mouth; It was no more betwixt God and them but this, Go up and dye.</p>
            <p>To conclude then, May all your practices appear to the world in a faithful compliance with what was truly imitable and praiſe-worthy in him. May the living Example of your dead Miniſter, be exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the lives of you his People. May you daily dreſs by his Glaſs, and walk in his pious and devout Foot-ſteps. May you all meet him with aſtoniſhing Joy, and behold him alſo with unutterable delight and comfort in the day of your great Audit, this is and ever ſhall be the hearty and affectionate ſupplication of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ſympathizing Friend and Servant,</hi> William Burkitt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Mildin,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. 10. 1679.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104311:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>HEB. xiii. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Remember them that have the rule over you, who have ſpoken to you the word of God, whoſe faith follow, conſidering the end of their Converſation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HOwever at the firſt appearance, the Text may ſeem not unfitly acommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the ſad and ſorrowful cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, in which you the People of this place do at preſent ſtand; yet it is no part of my intention by the reading of theſe words to exaſperate your grief, or revive your ſorrow for the loſs of your truly Reverend, and lately deceaſed Watchman; but rather to moderate and regulate your juſt ſorrow for him, whom without weeping eyes it had been a ſin in you to part with. That People have a hard and dry
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104311:6"/>haert indeed that can part with Gods Prophets without tears. Phyſicians tell us, that if Rheum be ſweetned it cannot hurt the Lungs; ſure I am, if ſorrow be ſanctified, it cannot hurt the heart, nor prejudice the ſoul: now that your ſorrow may be ſuch, it is my deſign in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here at your requeſt this day, to call you off from mourning for him, who wants neither the benefit nor benevolence of your Tears, to a juſt imitation of him; to tranſcribe his excellent pattern, in fair and legible Characters in your own lives.</p>
            <p>How lovely was that copy of Religion which he ſet before you in his dayly Converſation! So forcible was the Majeſty of that holineſs that ſhined forth in him, that it did extort a venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from its moſt violent Oppoſers; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victive alſo, that it pierced the very Conſciences of his Enemies, and conſtrained them whom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice only had made his Foes, tacitly to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that God was in him of a Truth. Know then that 'tis a poor and low evidence of your reſpects to him, ſhould you go with <hi>Mary</hi> to your dear friends Sepulchre, and there bedew his Coffin with your Tears: the higheſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of your ardent love to him, and of your unbounded and inexpreſſible gratitude to God for him, is to take up his exemplary graces, by a Chriſtian imitation, and to mourn more paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately that you are ſo unlike him, than that you have at preſent loſt him; that all your long converſes with him ſhould no more aſſimilate you to his own likeneſs.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104311:6"/>
            <p>Think it not, I beſeech you, a ſufficient and ſuitable return to almighty God, for ſive and thirty years injoyment of his miniſterial labours, to follow his Herſe to the Grave with a ſigh and a groan: believe it, God expects ſomewhat more at your hands for ſuch a mercy, than all this comes to; if you ſhall forget to obey his Counſels, if you ſhall neglect to follow his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; not only the duſt of his feet whilſt alive, but the very aſhes of his Grave now dead, will ſadly appear as a judicial teſtimony againſt you in the day of your account.</p>
            <p>What, is this all you can afford, to ſprinkle a tear upon the Herſe of ſo faithful a ſervant of Chriſt and of your ſouls? have you nothing but a ſew briny drops wherewith to preſerve and perpetuate his excellent memory beyond his Urn? will you ſuffer this burning and ſhining light, which was ſo ſignal an Ornament to the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick it ſo long ſtood in, to go out in ſilence like a Glow-worm at the Hedges bottom, with no greater noiſe than you make with your Eyes? I hope not ſo, but rather that you will remember him that ſo long had the Miniſterial Rule over you, who hath ſo often with an indefatigable indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and laborious diligence ſpoken to you the word of God, whoſe faith it is your higheſt wiſdom perſeveringly to follow, conſidering the bleſſed end of his Chriſtian converſation.</p>
            <p>In a word, I hope you will honour and hear him as long as ever he preaches to you, and then I am ſure you will not fail to do ſo ſtill, for with righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> he being dead, yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104311:7"/>yea dead as well as living he is ſtill your Preacher, his Shroud and Coffin are his Pulpit, his Grave and Tomb-ſtone are his Temple, and he ſtill preaches to you, though he lies in ſilence before you and utters never a word, I mean by his pious and moſt inſtructive example left among you, and by that fair character and good report, which he hath ſo deſervedly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with you, upon which account, allow me, I pray, the liberty to beſpeak you freely in the words of the great Apoſtle now read unto you, <hi>Remember them that have the Rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the word of God; whoſe faith follow conſidering the end of their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words contain the Apoſtles advice to the Chriſtian <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and in them to all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Chriſtians, how to manage their de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portment toward their Eccleſiaſtical Governors, whom God by death or perſecution at any time removes from them; and that is, firſt ever to preſerve their name and memory freſh among them as a precious treaſure, <hi>Remember them that have the Rule over you:</hi> Secondly, to propound their holy converſation to their daily view, in a Chriſtian imitation of thoſe Evangelical gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Moral vertues, which were ſo orient and exemplary in their Rulers lives, <hi>whoſe faith follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words you have four particulars obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104311:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſons exhorted, the Church of God; unto whom he mercifully affords the honour and happineſs of a Spiritual Guide and Ruler.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Duty exhorted to, and that is two ſold. (1.) To embalm their names with a precious memory, <hi>remember them, &amp;c.</hi> (2.) To imitate their Chriſtian Example, and tranſcribe it impartially into their own lives; <hi>whoſe faith follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is the pattern propounded to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians imitation; or the perſons deſcribed whom we ought thus to imitate and follow, and they are our Spiritual Rulers, deſcribed here to us by a double character; (1.) By their Miniſterial Office; <hi>who have ſpoken unto you the word of God</hi> (2.) By their Miniſterial Power, which they exerciſe by vertue of that Office, and that is to rule and govern the Flock committed by Chriſt to their care and charge; <hi>Remember them that have the Rule over you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Here is the Argument and Motive which the Apoſtle makes uſe of, to excite and quicken a People to this commendable imitation of their Spiritual Rulers, and that is drawn from the happy concluſion which they make, when they have finiſhed their teſtimony at death; they go off the publick Stage with honour and applauſe: this I conceive lies coucht and comprehended in the laſt words, <hi>Conſidering the end of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtrait limits of our time will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a diſtinct handling of all the foregoing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. I ſhall therefore propound one gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104311:8"/>note to your obſervance, which (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) is the principal intendment of the Text. Take it thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is the ſtanding Duty of that people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>whom God hath honoured with the long enjoyment of a Spiritual Guide and Ruler, perſeveringly to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Faith, and to imitate his exemplary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
               <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>The original word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we tranſlate to follow and imitate, doth not ſimply ſignifie to remark and obſerve anothers actions, but to perform a work according to example and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern: a Metaphor as ſome conceive borrowed from Theatres, where the Stage-players ſtudy with the greateſt accuracy and exactneſs, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the geſtures and diſpoſitions of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom they deſign to perſonate and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: to the faithful exerciſe of which induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care, doth the Apoſtle exhort all Chriſtians, in their imitation of thoſe whom God hath ſet over them, in whatever was truly exemplary and praiſe-worthy in them; when here he bids us <hi>follow thier Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will conſult the ſacred Scriptures, you will find this Duty frequently recommended to, and as highly commended in the Chriſtian; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how ſtrictly it is recommended to our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Be ye followers of me, even as I alſo am of Chriſt:</hi> note alſo how the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Duty is commended by the ſame Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Ye became followers of us, and of the Lord, having received the word in much affliction,</hi> &amp;c. that is (as I humbly conceive)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104311:8"/>ye followed us with a reſolute perſeverance in the ſame thorny path of perſecution and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Goſpel ſake, in which we before you had traced the Foot-ſteps of the ſuffering Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the more diſtinct and methodical handling of the Note propounded, I ſhall attempt to give you a ſatisfactory reſolution to theſe two inquiries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall inquire how and after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are a People concerned, to imitate and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the pattern and example of their Spiritual Rulers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From what Motives, and upon what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations are they obliged ſo to do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Inquiry; How and after what manner ought a people to imitate and follow their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Rulers?</p>
            <p>To this I ſhall return a double Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Negative: The beſt of Miniſters being but men at the beſt, therefore their peoples imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them and their Example muſt not be an univerſal but a limited imitation; with this juſt caution the great Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own example to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> view;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>be ye followers of me, as I alſo am of Chriſt;</hi> as if he had ſaid, If at any time you find me your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Guide ſtepping aſide, and walking unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that uniform pattern of obedience which the holy Jeſus ſet before both me and you in his own holy and immaculate life, take heed that you decline my example, and follow not my foot-ſteps.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104311:9"/>
            <p>Indeed the Doctors of the Romiſh Synagogue do peremptorily oblige their followers to believe whatever they (as infallible Dictators) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to them, be it never ſo unreaſonable; and to practiſe alſo whatever they ſet in exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple before them, be it never ſo ridiculous and abſurd. Verily they impoſe the ſame ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious terms upon the people of their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.2.</note> which <hi>Nahaſh</hi> once offered to the men of <hi>Jabeſh-gilead,</hi> that every one ſhall put out his right Eye (Reaſon) that ſo they may be the more fit for their blind devotion; yea both Eyes if the Church command it; the Eye of Senſe too muſt at leaſt be disbelieved, otherwiſe that grand affront to humane nature the doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation had never obtained credence in the world.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God your Miniſters have more integrity, than thus magiſterially to impoſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon your belief or upon your practice. We charitably warn you of your danger, if you try not both our Doctrine and our Manners, by the infallible touchſtone of the Holy Scriptures, before you believe the one or imitate the other. We freely acknoweldge, and impartially confeſs that we are men of like paſſions and infirmities with your ſelves, and as obnoxious to error through ignorance, as we are to ſin through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity.</p>
            <p>You are not then, you ſee, either command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, or encouraged by us, to imitate and follow your ſpiritual Guides univerſally, and in all things: but with a due reſtriction and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104311:9"/>juſt limitation, you are to follow your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters no further than they follow their infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Miniſter, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively. A peoples imitation of their Preachers exemplary Pattern ought to have this threefold ſignature inſtampt and impreſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ought to be a regular and uniform imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; you are not to follow him univerſally in all his actions, but in the impartial exerciſe of all his graces; this Counſel the holy Apoſtle gives, Phil. 4.8. <hi>Whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, what ſoever things are of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; if there be any virtue, praiſe or comelineſs</hi> in his Actions, thoſe things you muſt think up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Remember to follow your Spiritual Guide in that even path of piety, wherein he hath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly followed the Captain of your ſalvation. Hypocriſie ſingles out one grace and ſhuns ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but ſincerity diſcovers it ſelf by an uniform care and endeavour to tranſcribe all, and doth nothing by partiality.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be a vigorous and induſtrious imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: indeed to imitate ſinners in an evil way, requires no great pains, in regard of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral vent and tendency of our natures to ſin and vanity; as alſo in regard of the pronity of the Tempter to ſolicite and invite forth our innate corruption into act and exerciſe. But to follow a Chriſtian in what is eminently good, requires a vigorous intention of mind; and all the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour faculties of our ſouls muſt be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed induſtriouſly in that noble exerciſe: here
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104311:10"/>our underſtandings muſt be exerciſed to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the radiant excellency of thoſe Chriſtian Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ſhine forth in others: here muſt our judgements be imployed to diſcover by the light of Scripture and Reaſon, what is to be choſen, and what to be eſchewed in the Pattern we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to follow: here our affections alſo muſt be concerned in taking a daily pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, to hold with an unwearied hand the Glaſs of their holy lives continually before us, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to dreſs our Souls by it. Certainly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all this, requires a ſoul fortified with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and armed with ſuch an impregnable reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as no difficulties can diſmay or vanquiſh.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It ought to be a conſtant and perſevering imitation: be always endeavouring to keep your Miniſters example freſh in memory, and make this duty your daily work and conſtant practice. So much, I conceive, is implyed in that Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical injunction, Heb. 6.12. <hi>Be ye followers of them, who through faith and patience inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes:</hi> that is, follow the Saints with the ſame Chriſtian patience, and perſevering faith, with which they inherit the glorious accompliſhment of all the promiſes.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly ſhewn you how, and after what manner a People are obliged to follow the Religious foot-ſteps of their exemplary Guides, The</p>
            <p n="2">2. Inquiry followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> from what Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and upon what Conſiderations they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned thus to do.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104311:10"/>
            <p>To which I anſwer, A People lye under a threefold obligation to this Duty, <hi>viz.</hi> in regard of God, in relation to themſelves, and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of God, Becauſe this is one of his principal ends in beſtowing ſuch gracious qualifications upon his Miniſters; yea, Gods great deſign in ſending his Meſſengers amongſt a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is, that by the holineſs of their example, as well as by the purity of their Doctrine, they may win ſouls to a love of Righteouſneſs: this is the Duty which <hi>Timothy</hi> is exhorted to, when the Apoſtle bids him hold forth the word of life; that is, the purity of it in his Doctrine, and the power of it in his Converſation: from hence, no doubt, it is that Chriſt Compares his Apoſtles to lights, <hi>ye are the light of the world:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> an alluſion (as may be probably conjectured) to Torches held out in a dark night, to direct Paſſengers their way; or to fires upon a Beacon near the Sea-coaſt, to prevent the bewildered Mariners ſplitting upon Rocks, and ſuffering Shipwrack. Believe it, God doth not only beſtow his graces upon his Miniſters for their own ſakes, to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them for their future happineſs and glory, but he deſigns alſo your advantage by thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments; ſo that a people do apparently ſin againſt the great end and purpoſe of Gods love and kindneſs, in ſending his Ambaſſadors among them; if they do not fruitfully improve their Religious Example ſet before them: for verily your Miniſters gifts are a talent, for which you, as well as they, are reſponſible to God: yea, you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104311:11"/>are as highly accountable to God for the Holy Example they ſet before you, as you are for that ſacred <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> the doctrine of faith, I mean, which they deliver to you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In relation to your ſelves: Without a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian imitation of the ſtedfaſtneſs of their faith, and the exemplarineſs of their converſation, whom God hath ſet over you, and made patterns of ſolid piety unto you; that which was your mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and priviledge in the enjoyment, will appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently tend to the dreadful aggravation of your ſin, and the eternal heightning of your account. St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his famous funeral Oration for the Saints departed, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 11. tells us of <hi>Noah, verſe</hi> 5. that he condemned the world, which no doubt he did by his practice, as well as by his preaching: indeed he preached by his hand as well as with his tongue; his building of the Ark was a daily viſible Sermon to that unreclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able generation: with what ſcoffing deriſion did the old world laugh at <hi>Noah</hi> for his Ark, and tell one another in ſport, that too much holineſs had made the old man mad: and that all the alarms of a flood approaching, were but the idle dreams of the doting Prophet? yet his example not followed, brought vengeance upon that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to extremity.</p>
            <p>Think then of this all you the people of this place, who have ſo long enjoyed a Preacher of Righteouſneſs among you, and all that while have found him a faithful witneſs from God unto you; for not receiving his teſtimony, you muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to find him another day an eternal witneſs for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104311:11"/>God againſt you. Believe it timely, if you be not awakened to a fruitful contention of being like him, in all that was truly imitable and praiſe-worthy in him, verily your ſins would not have been accented with ſuch an aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted guilt (as they will then be) had you never known him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A people are obliged thus perſeveringly to follow the holy example of their Spiritual Guides, with a reference unto them; and that in two reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that your Chriſtian imitation of their inſtructive example will conduce very much to make up their loſs, and render them leſs miſt and wanted in the world. I doubt not but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you are juſtly ſenſible of the ſeverity of that ſtroke, which the hand of Almighty God hath given your Town in your late Miniſters death; yet think not, I pray, your loſs irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for be aſſured it is very much within the compaſs of your power, to repair and make up your own loſs: ſtand but you all up, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in your diſtinct and ſeveral capacities for God (as he did) by a publick owning of his ways and worſhip; fill you up the breach made by the death of him with your gracious influence, and his abſence will be the better born. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſervable what our dying Saviours comfort was upon the bed of his Croſs; next to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the divine preſence, this revived his ſoul that he had a Seed in the world which ſhould ſtand up and appear for God, after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Pſal. 22.30. <hi>My ſeed ſhall ſerve him;</hi> as if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104311:12"/>our Lord had ſaid, Although I am taking my fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal farewell of this world, yet I ſhall leave a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual generation behind me, that will carry on my Fathers work in the world, and build up my ſpiritual kingdom, when I ſhall be at reſt. And I am ſure it did not a little conduce to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your dying Miniſters ſpirit, when he had death before him in immediate proſpect, to hope upon good grounds that he (as a Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſhould leave many Children behind him, to carry on the work of Chriſt in the world, when his head ſhould be laid among the clods.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In as much as your Chriſtian care to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate your Miniſters pattern, will be the beſt and fulleſt commendation you can beſtow upon their perſon; it is indeed no leſs the duty, than the commendation of a people, to embalm the names of their dead Miniſters with a precious memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who have worn out amongſt them with uſe, and not with ruſt; equity as well as ingenuity requires this, that when they are in Heaven, they ſhould live in their good name on earth, as when they were on earth, they lived by their good heart in Heaven. Yet withal I crave leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe a double caution.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That your higheſt commendations and praiſes of them without a Chriſtian endeavour to exemplifie and imitate whatever you obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved praiſe-worthy in them, is but an unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble complement, of no more fragrancy, than a handful of Flowers which the innocent Child ſtrows upon its Parents grave, which make the Corps ſmell not at all the ſweeter. Nay,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104311:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. To commend and not to imitate, is not only diſingenuity but hypocriſie, not only bare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, but which is far worſe, 'tis ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; for if you do believe that to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellent in your Miniſter which you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him for, why do you then not imitate it? if you apprehend it not excellent, why do you then commend it? ſo that thy tongue doth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bely thy heart, or elſe thy life doth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict thy tongue. To cure which vanity, apply your ſelves to an induſtrious following of what the word of God and your own Conſciences tell you did deſerve your notice; and let your own works, as well as his, praiſe him in the gate.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The Application.</head>
               <p>From all that hath been ſpoken I infer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is no leſs than our obliged duty to bleſs almighty God with hearty gratulation and praiſe, for the pious lives, and exemplary deaths, of ſuch whom his divine grace hath made patterns of holineſs to us in the world. Certainly to bleſs his holy name for all his Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants departed this life in his faith and fear, is ſo far from ſmelling of the rank ſuperſtition of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as ſome have weakly thought) that it is matter of poſitive duty to expreſs our thankfulneſs for ſuch excellent helps to further us in our way towards Heaven. Precepts may be dark and obſcure, but precepts exemplified are plain and facil: the holy example of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104311:13"/>Saints afford us a double help in running our Chriſtian Race.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As they aſſure us that whatever the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel requires at our hands, is a poſſible attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the ſame aſſiſtance that enabled them, ſtands ready to ſuccour us: ſo that the poor and little excuſes of difficulty and impoſſibility in what the Goſpel enjoyns, are hereby obviated, whilſt we behold thoſe vertues and graces flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in others, with an happy facility, from which we would excuſe our ſelves upon thoſe weak pretences.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that examples do inſpirit us with life and vigour. <hi>Miltiades</hi> his victories would not ſuffer <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to ſleep: ſo highly did the ſucceſs of the one animate and inflame the zeal of the other. Bleſs we God then for that cloud of Witneſſes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> (with the great Apoſtle) which doth at once both encourage our endeavours, and alſo aſſure us of ſucceſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Inference. I next infer from what hath been already offered, how exact and circumſpect the Miniſters of Chriſt ought, and are obliged to be in that example which they daily ſet before their people. O how highly are we all concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to oblige our ſelves to an eminent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary piety of converſation! the Reaſon is obvious, becauſe the eyes of all our Flock not only are, but ought to be upon us: our miſtakes then, are not like the errors of a Pocket-watch, which miſlead only a ſingle perſon, but like thoſe of a Town Clock, which miſguides a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104311:13"/>What a ſtrange curioſity and holy niceneſs was there in the election of thoſe who were under the Law admitted to ſerve at the Altar; if there wore the leaſt blemiſh in the Head, Eye, Hand or Foot, they were forthwith excluded from thoſe Levitical ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations;
<note place="margin">Lev. 21.17, 18, 19.</note> if there were not an exact ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry of parts, they muſt not ſet a foot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the floor of the holy place. What, think you, was the Goſpel of that Ceremonial Rite but this, to intimate and ſignifie that inward purity of heart, and unſpotted inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of life which Almighty God expects in the Evangelical Prieſthood? Certainly the Spiritual blemiſhes of Gods immediate Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants under the Goſpel, are not a leſs eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore to the Divine Purity, than thoſe Legal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, which did deny the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi> an allowed acceſs to Gods Altar, during the Ceremonial Law. Conſider we then, that our actions have an aptitude to make a deeper impreſſion upon the minds of our people, than our words: Thoſe that do forget our Doctrine, will be ſure to remember our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, at leaſt ſo far, as to produce it boldly by way of Apology for themſelves, when they walk in any path of Impiety and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <hi>Theophylact</hi> in his commentary upon thoſe words, <hi>Chriſt opened his mouth and taught,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.2.</note> makes this Query, whether the firſt words were not ſuperfluous; he anſwers No, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104311:14"/>although Chriſt, when he opened his mouth taught, yet he did teach, when he did not open his mouth, <hi>viz.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) by his life; ſo then there is a preaching life as well as a preaching doctrine: if Religion be taught by the firſt but not by the ſecond, we fadly diſappoint the end of what is ſpoken; and thus <hi>Penelope</hi> like, what we do in the day we may undo in the night, in works of darkneſs. Yet let it not be inferred from hence, that the Miniſters unworthineſs doth make void his Office, and evacuate his Commiſſion; for the efficacy of the ſacred Function de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends not upon our dignity, but on the ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of Divine Grace: yet as to his own ſoul it renders all his labours fruitleſs. Admit his Doctrine be ſound; yet an Heterodox Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation will carry an Orthodox Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Hell. In a word, though like a crackt Bell he may be inſtrumental to ring others to Heaven, yet for himſelf there is no remedy, but to the fire he muſt go, either for his refining or his condemnation. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this, the Throne and the Pulpit, above all places call for holineſs: the Prince and the Preacher, above all perſons, are moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to God for their Example.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Inference. I infer from hence in the laſt place how ſignal your obligations are to Almighty God for the long enjoyment of that exemplary pattern of all true piety and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104311:14"/>(your deceaſed Miniſter I mean) whom (for your ſins I fear) he hath lately taken from you. Shew now your obedience to God, your reſpects to him, your kindneſs and charity to your own ſouls, by a zealous and faithful care to tranſcribe impartially in your own lives whatever was truly imitable in your Miniſters. And not to carry you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the confines of the Text, let me earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſpeak your Chriſtian compliance with a double duty here injoyned.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To follow his faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To imitate his exemplary converſation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Follow his faith, and that in a double reſpect, in the ſoundneſs of his faith, and in the ſtedfaſtneſs of his faith.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Follow him in the ſoundneſs of his faith. The faith which he perſeveringly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and taught, was that Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs; that faith which owns God for its immediate Author, and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for its infallible Rule: the faith that was once delivered to the Saints, which is not the reſult of phanſie and imagination, but the product of an eternal Counſel, which was confirmed by the miracles, and ſealed with the blood of a Saviour. In a word, that faith which he ſo zealouſly taught, had ſure footing in the holy Scriptures. When-ever he propounded any truth which required not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the aſſent of your underſtandings, but alſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104311:15"/>the obedience and adoration of your faith, he conſtantly ſhewed you the Canon of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures for its confirmation. If any then (which God forbid) ſhould appear after him in this place, and attempt the proſelyting of you to another Goſpel, or to any new doctrine of faith foreign to the Scriptures, ſhould he pretend to the authority of a commiſſioned Angel from Heaven, let him be held accurſed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Follow him in the ſtedfaſtneſs of his faith. The ſame rule of faith which he laid before you at his firſt coming amongſt you, he lived and preached by to the day of his death: and this I take the greater liberty to aſſert, becauſe ſome perſons have not bluſht to tell the world publickly, that ſince his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the diſcipline of the Church, he had apoſtatized and revolted from that faith which he had formerly profeſt and taught; but be ye all aſſured, that as to the great fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Faith and Religion he was ever the ſame, and what he taught you to his laſt breath, I doubt not but he ſtood ready to confirm and ſeal with his blood, even in the fierceſt flames of martyrdom, if God had call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to that fiery trial.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Imitate his Chriſtian Converſation. My meaning is, exempliſie thoſe Evangelical Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Chriſtian Vertues in your lives, which did ſo oriently ſhine forth in his. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a few:</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104311:15"/>
               <p n="1">1. His Eminent Humility. This was the garment which covered all his excellent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, although indeed their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was rendred more conſpicuous and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by caſting this veil over it. Oh what mean thoughts had he of himſelfe and was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly content, but deſirous alſo that others ſhould have ſo too: no man ever expreſſed ſo low a value of his worth and merits as himſelf did. Every thing in others that was good, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired as excellent, whilſt the ſame or better in himſelf, he thought not unworthily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned: his Eyes were full of his own defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencies and others perfections. In a word, he was a lowly Valley, ſweetly planted, well watered, richly fruitful; imitate him then herein, and by a holy emulation ſtudy to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel him in this adorning Grace; and for your help herein recollect what you heard from him in his elaborate Diſcourſes among you upon Phil. 2.5. <hi>Let this mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> this humble mind.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His extenſive Love: this grace did vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly exert it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His love to God, he loved him exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, whom he could not love exceſſively, having ſuch high and raiſed apprehenſions of his Makers excellencies, as cauſed him to judge his prime and beſt affections unworthy to be placed upon ſo Divine an Object.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104311:16"/>
               <p n="2">2. His Love to the holy Jeſus: this was ſuch a Seraphick and Divine fire in his ſoul, as did marvellouſly conſume his love to the world and all ſublunary comforts. You are witneſſes, and all that knew him, in how emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a meaſure and degree the world was crucified unto him, and he unto the world, by the Croſs of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His love to ſouls; this was it, no doubt, that made him ſo indefatigable both in his Study and the Pulpit; from hence it was, that the Throne of Grace, his Study, the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit and his ſick Neighbours, had the whole of his time divided amongſt them, and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. His unbounded love to all Chriſtians, though they differed in their ſentiments from him: he loved Chriſtians for their Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and did adore the Image of his Saviour where-ever he ſaw it in any of his members, unhappily perſecuting one another with hard names and characters of reproach. How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten did he publickly deplore and bewail, that the greateſt meaſure of love that is found at this day amongſt the profeſſors of the Croſs, was not true Chriſtian love, but only love of a party! Follow him then in the impartial exerciſe of this grace, and for your help there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in remember what he taught you from Eph. 5.2. <hi>And walk in love as Chriſt alſo hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us;</hi> and as you have any regard for the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104311:16"/>Author of your profeſſion, take heed that a ſpirit of Diviſion (now) crowd not in among you: your unity is your ſtrength as well as your beauty; perſiſt therefore, I beſeech you, in that Chriſtian Order amongſt your ſelves, in which it was his great ambition all his days to preſerve and keep you. Timely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the crafty deſign of the ſubtile Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſouls, who will take this occaſion (if poſſible) now the Spiritual Parents is out of the way, to ſet the Children together by the ears.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His diffuſive Charity: his Alms were as exuberant as his Love: miſery and want where-ever he met them, did ſufficiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear their objects to him; he was none of thoſe that hide their faces from the Poor, nor of the number of them, who ſatisfie their Conſciences with a ſingle exerciſe of their Charity once a year, but daily were the emanations of his Bounty. Yet although he caſt the ſeeds of his Charity upon all ſorts of ground, he ſowed them thickeſt upon Gods encloſure; my meaning is, he did good unto all, <hi>but eſpecially to thoſe that were of the Houſhold of Faith.</hi> Make him herein, and his example the pattern of your daily imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for the world which is chained toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by intermingled love, will ſoon ſhatter and fall in pieces if Charity ſhall once fail and dye: and for your better help herein,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104311:17"/>call over thoſe potent Arguments for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of this Evangelical Duty, which he urged upon you, from that Apoſtolical injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Heb. 13.16. <hi>But to do good, and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. His perſevering diligence and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his place and ſtation. You could not but obſerve, that his whole diſpoſal of himſelf was to perpetual induſtry and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; he not only avoided idleneſs, but ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a forcible antipathy againſt it, and was often recommending it to you with great concern and vigour in his publick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, to be always furniſht with ſomewhat to do; <hi>ut te inveniat ſemper Diabolus occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> that the Devil may never find thee at leiſure to liſten to his temptations, as St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> adviſeth. The idle mans brain being, in truth, not only the Devils Shop, but his Kingdom too, a Model of, and an Appendage unto Hell; a place (like that) given up to torture and miſchief. As to himſelf, his chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt recreation was variety of work; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thoſe portions of time, which the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of nature, and of civil life extorted from him, there was not a minute of the day which he left vacant. Now to extimulate your zeal to a pious imitation of him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo; let me admoniſh you to ruminate upon thoſe accurate Sermons you heard from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104311:17"/>him upon St. Mat. 20.6. <hi>Why ſtand ye here all the day idle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. His tender ſympathie with the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church of Chriſt. Like a true ſon of <hi>Zion</hi> he could not rejoyce when his Mother mourned, he daily felt as much by ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as he did by ſenſe; and no wonder, for he that hath a ſtock going in the Churches Ship, cannot but lament and quake at every ſtorm: Oh how frequent were his enquiries after her, how fervent were his prayers for her, how bowelly and compaſſionate were his mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings over her! The deplorable condition of the Church and Nation lay exceeding near his heart, both living and dying; he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their happineſs and welfare above his chief joy. Now in order to your attaining the ſame Chriſt-like temper with him, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently meditate upon what you heard from him, upon <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 1.4. where the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathizing Prophet refuſeth to drink wine, when the afflicted Church drank water.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And laſtly, to ſum up all, imitate him in his daily care and endeavour to live Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in all his capacities. As a Miniſter, ye are Witneſſes, and God alſo, how faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, how conſcientiouſly he diſcharged his duty towards you. In the exerciſe of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Function, if cenſure it ſelf be able to tax him for any neglect, it muſt be in no more frequent viſiting his Flock, from which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104311:18"/>nothing but a weak body kept him, not a proud or unwilling mind; the obſtruction he met with in this part of his Duty from his tender habit of body (which would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him ſo frequently to perform it as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired) was his great ſorrow both living and dying; yet having this to comfort him, that the frailty of his body was his affliction, but not his ſin. Conſider him in his next relative Capacity, as a Child, how dutiful and obſequious! O how great was that tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of veneration and reſpect which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly paid to the hoary hairs of his aged Parents! As a Husband, how tender and compaſſionate; as a Parent, how indulgent and affectionate; as a Miniſter, how kind and munificent! Thus was he univerſally good in all ſtations, and liv'd Religion in very capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. And if you deſire to imitate him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo, as becomes you, dreſs then your ſouls by that Glaſs daily, which his dying hand laſt held up before your Eyes, I mean by Heavenly meditation, make thoſe uſeful truths your own, which you laſt heard from him upon Titus 2.12. <hi>That denying ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent world:</hi> Which Chriſtian Leſſon, if it ſhall be as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically learnt by you, as it was faithfully taught by him; I will be bold to ſay thus much in the ſingular commendation of you his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104311:18"/>that you will thereby give the world a convictive inſtance, that this age hath Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues as ſtupendious as its Vices.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>Thus I have given my ſelf the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of doing my Duty, in propounding your Miniſters example to your Chriſtian view. Let none cenſoriouſly ſay, I have been all this while painting the Prophets Sepulchre. No, but deſcribing the Prophet himſelf, and with this ſingle and ſincere intention, that you may timely know, you have had a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord among you; a perſon that had <hi>(omnia in ſe ſempiterna praeter corpuſculum)</hi> all things living and laſting to eternity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his body, which was the only thing he had ſubject to mortality, and beſides which, nothing of him doth ſee corruption. 'Twill be below the merit of his perſon, as well as the greatneſs of our loſs, to celebrate his death in womaniſh complaints, or indeed by any verbal lamentations; nor can any thing beſeem his memory but what is Sacred and Divine, as his Writings are. May his juſt fame from them, and from his vertues, be precious to all ſucceeding ages; and when Elegies committed to the truſt of Marble, ſhall be as illegible as if they had been writ in Water, when all ſtately Pyramids ſhall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104311:19"/>be diſſolved in duſt, and all the venerable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of Antiquity be devoured by the corroding Teeth of Time, then let this ſhort Character, deſcribing him in his beſt and fulleſt Portraicture, remain of him, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was A CHRISTIAN IN COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLEAT ARMOUR.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104311:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
